Guide to the New-York Historical Society Press Clippings 1843-2014 NYHS-RG 7
New-York Historical Society
New-York Historical Society press clippings
1843-2014
New-York Historical Society
NYHS-RG 7
48 Linear feet in 50 boxes of various sizes
The New-York Historical Society press clippings record group includes material compiled regularly by N-YHS into scrapbooks, subject files and binders from published sources from about 1870 to 2014, with some clippings as early as 1843. Subjects include exhibitions, lectures, publications, and other programs; acquisitions of new collections or objects; building construction, management controversies, and other institutional matters; and leadership changes, obituaries, and other matters connected to individuals. The record group provides insight from over a century into the extent of press coverage of N-YHS and press perceptions of the organization and its programs, and a broad overview of events in N-YHS's history as presented in the press.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Arrangement Note
The New-York Historical Society press clippings record group is organized in three series:
Series I. Scrapbooks, 1843-1991
Series II. Subject Files, 1968-2013
Series III. Media Coverage Binders, 2004-2009, 2013-2014
Scope and Contents Note
The New-York Historical Society press clippings record group includes material compiled regularly by N-YHS from published sources from about 1870 to about 2014. The record group also holds some clippings from as early as 1843. The material includes clippings and tearsheets from newspapers, general interest magazines, museum, antiques, and other specialist journals, and other print matter. These clippings are compiled in 28 boxed volumes of scrapbooks and, from about 1970, in subject-oriented files and binders. Although perhaps most of the clippings are from New York sources, there are a substantial number of clippings from other U.S. cities and even from the international press (accordingly, many of these are not in English). The record group also holds a small number of reprints and copies of essays written about N-YHS and its collections in books and journals.
The subjects of the articles in the record group are wide-ranging. Topics relate to N-YHS exhibitions, lectures, publications, and other programs and events; acquisitions of new collections or objects; implementation of major new initiatives (e.g. the Field Exploration Committee, circa 1917-1938); building construction on Central Park West (1900s and 1930s); management controversies (e.g., Mrs. Van Rensselaer's reform movement of circa 1917 and the financial difficulties of the 1980s-1990s); and recognitions, leadership changes, obituaries (e.g., the death of Director Alexander Wall in 1944), and other matters connected to individuals. Overall, the record group provides insight into the extent of press coverage of N-YHS, press perceptions of the organization and its programs, and a broad overview and narrative of events in N-YHS's history as presented in the press.
Related Archival Materials Note
This finding aid relates to just one record group of the New-York Historical Society archives. For information about the other record groups and for overall information about the archives, please see the Guide to the New-York Historical Society Archives (NYHS-RG Archives). Other record groups that are processed and available to researchers and are especially related to the New-York Historical Society press clippings (NYHS-RG 7) are as follows:
For press releases (1941-1993) and press kits (1976-1994) produced by N-YHS and its Public Relations Department, see New-York Historical Society public relations material (NYHS-RG 8).
Learned institutions and societies -- Press coverage -- New York (State) -- New York.; Libraries and institutions -- Press coverage -- New York (State) -- New York.; New York (N.Y.) -- History -- Societies, etc.; Clippings (information artifacts); Scrapbooks.; New-York Historical Society -- Archives.; New-York Historical Society -- Press coverage.
- Series I. Scrapbooks, 1843-1991; 38 Linear feet in 28 boxed volumes
  Scope and Contents Note
  The Scrapbook series includes 28 boxed volumes of clippings from newspapers, general interest magazines, museum, antiques, and other specialist journals, and other print matter concerning New-York Historical Society and New York's history. Although there are articles dating from as early as 1843, the regular content of the scrapbooks appears to begin principally in 1871. The scrapbooks advance with increasing consistency and quantity well into the twentieth century, pausing about 1972, and then picking up with some final volumes covering various years in the 1980s and 1990s, ending with 1991.
  Articles related to N-YHS concern exhibitions, lectures, and other programs and events; acquisitions of new collections or objects; activities of the Field Exploration Committee and other initiatives; building construction, management controversies, and other organizational issues; and recognitions, leadership changes, obituaries, and other matters connected to individuals. Newspapers represented are principally from New York City and Brooklyn (e.g., Herald, Evening Post, Tribune, American, Sun, Times, World, New York Commercial, Evening Telegram, Citizen (Brooklyn), Standard Union (Brooklyn), Times (Brooklyn), and others). Other cities and states are also represented (e.g., Providence, Cleveland, Baltimore, Philadelphia, San Francisco, various New Jersey papers, and others). Some clippings retained their transmittal information so the work of providers such as Henry Romeike, Inc., Argus Pressclipping Bureau, Selective Service Clipping Co., and Burrelle's is evident.
  Arrangement Note
  The scrapbooks are arranged in chronological order, although this is only approximate for the first six books as their date ranges do not proceed in a strictly sequential manner. The titles of the volumes used in the container list were taken, when present, from the scrapbooks; [bracketed] titles were supplied by the archivist.
  The clippings in the scrapbooks, especially those from the nineteenth century and into the mid-twentieth century, are very fragile and must be handled with great care. Many clippings, especially in the earliest volumes, are not secured to pages of the scrapbook, but are simply inserted at various points. Clippings that come loose or break during use should be brought to the attention of the reference librarian.
  - [Clippings], 1858-1859 (Offsite-box 1, Volume 1)
    Includes clippings concerning notable New York City events and other matters of the time, articles about New York's history, and just a few articles about N-YHS.
  - Newspaper Cuttings Related to the NY Historical Society, 1844-1909 (Offsite-box 2, Volume 1)
    The core scrapbook includes clippings from 1871-1907, with loose clippings at the front of the album ranging from 1844 to 1909. The most interesting of these early clippings are a set from 1855 relating to the laying of the cornerstone of N-YHS's 2nd Ave building, and a November 1844 Daily Tribune article about a dinner held by N-YHS at the New-York Hotel, with seating diagram. Includes a photograph of the 2nd Ave building in 1904.
  - [N-YHS Clippings], 1899-1900, 1905, 1907-1911, 1916-1918 (Offsite-box 3, Volume 1)
    The core of the scrapbook includes the years 1907-11, with loose clippings at the back of the album or miscellaneous pages including other years.
  - [N-YHS Clippings], 1911-1917 (Offsite-box 4, Volume 1)
  - N-YHS Clippings, 1905-1907, 1912-1921 (Offsite-box 5, Volume 1)
  - N-YHS Clippings, 1843, 1921-1927 (Offsite-box 6, Volume 1)
    Includes clips about the Edwin Smith Medical Papyrus and other N-YHS Egyptian holdings, Field Exploration Committee, and advertisements placed by N-YHS in various papers soliciting documents, etc. from the public. Includes pages from the New York Herald of April 17, 1843, that include Albert Gallatin and Daniel Webster's remarks on the John Jay North Eastern boundary map (also reproduced in the paper).
  - N-YHS Clippings, 1928-1935 (Offsite-box 7, Volume 1)
  - N-YHS Clippings, 1935-1939 (Offsite-box 8, Volume 1)
    Includes articles about the construction and opening of the expanded building.
  - N-YHS Clippings, 1939-1941 (Offsite-box 9, Volume 1)
    Includes the transcript of the Oct 19, 1940, radio interview with Alexander Wall, Jr. about N-YHS and the transcript of a radio interview with museum curator H. Maxson Holloway about an exhibition of campaign objects.
  - N-YHS Clippings, 1941-1943 (Offsite-box 10, Volume 1)
  - N-YHS Clippings, 1943-1949 (Offsite-box 11, Volume 1)
    Many pages in the album are stuck together. Loose matter inserted in pages are stuck on underlying documents. Assistance from conservation staff is needed to use this volume.
  - N-YHS Clippings, 1949-1952 (Offsite-box 12, Volume 1)
    Includes New York Subways Advertising Co. ads for N-YHS (1952).
  - N-YHS Clippings, 1952-1954 (Offsite-box 13, Volume 1)
    Includes New York Subways Advertising Co. ads for N-YHS (1953-1954).
  - N-YHS Clippings, 1954-1956 (Offsite-box 14, Volume 1)
  - N-YHS Clippings, 1956-1958 (Offsite-box 15, Volume 1)
  - [N-YHS Clippings], 1958-1959 (Offsite-box 16, Volume 1)
  - [N-YHS Clippings], 1959-1961 (Offsite-box 17, Volume 1)
  - N-YHS Board of Trustees Clippings, 1942-1962 (Offsite-box 18, Volume 1)
    Includes obituaries and articles about honors and recognitions received by individual trustees and about their positions outside their N-YHS roles. Also includes articles about the death of Alexander Wall.
  - N-YHS Scrap Book, 1962-1966 (Offsite-box 19, Volume 1)
  - [N-YHS Clippings], 1967-1972 (Offsite-box 20, Volume 1)
  - Press Clippings, 1981-1983 (Offsite-box 21, Volume 1)
  - [Press Clippings], 1988 (Offsite-box 21, Volume 2)
  - Press Book, 1989 (Offsite-box 22, Volume 1)
  - Press Book, 1989 (Offsite-box 22, Volume 2)
  - Press Book, 1990 (Offsite-box 23, Volume 1)
  - Press Book, 1990-1991 (Offsite-box 23, Volume 2)
  - Press Clippings Book, 1990-1991 (Offsite-box 24, Volume 1)
  - [Press Clippings Book], 1991 (Offsite-box 24, Volume 2)
- Series II. Subject Files, 1968-2013; 7.67 Linear feet
  The folders were kept in their original order, which was chronological, though there are some minor exceptions at points in the order. The series was minimally processed so the documents within the folders remain, for the most part, as found, with no particular order to them. Not all clippings in each folder were reviewed for their dates so the date ranges shown in the container list, though generally accurate, may not be precise in all instances.
  The Subject Files include clippings and tearsheets from newspapers, magazines, newsletters, and other publications concerning various N-YHS matters. The bulk of the files relate to exhibitions or other N-YHS programs and events. Many of the clippings in the exhibition files are articles about or reviews of the program, but many clippings are just brief notices from published event listings and the like.
  In addition to the specific exhibition or other topical files, each year in the series from 1970 forward includes a file of general clippings. These include a broad mix of subjects, from general institutional matters to passing references to N-YHS in articles or published listings to items of only tangential interest. N-YHS's financial difficulties and other organizational issues of the 1980s and 1990s attracted much press coverage; these articles are primarily found in topical files, but some are in the general clippings as well.
  Although the bulk, by far, of the series consists of original or photocopied clippings from sources outside of N-YHS, some of the files also include documents from N-YHS's Public Relations Department, such as press releases and summaries of references in the press (called press round-ups or coverage reports), especially for events such as exhibitions. Some documents include brief staff notes, internal memos, or press correspondence related to coverage, especially for exhibitions. A very few folders include exhibition checklists, labels, booklets, or other material directly connected to the event; documents of this kind are noted at the folder level in the container list.
  - General Clippings, 1968-1971 (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - General Clippings, 1972-1973 (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - General Clippings, 1974 (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - General Clippings, 1975 (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - 200 Years of Toys in America, 1972 (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - New York to 1765: River, Bowery, Mill, and Beaver, 1973-1974 (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - Miniatures and Medals, 1973 (Box 25, Folder 7)
  - Eyewitness News of the Civil War, 1973 (Box 25, Folder 8)
  - Conservation Grant, 1973 (Box 25, Folder 9)
  - John Rogers: Household Gods, 1973 (Box 25, Folder 10)
  - Folk Art, 1973 (Box 25, Folder 11)
  - Summershow: The American Landscape, 1973 (Box 25, Folder 12)
  - Audubon: Birds of America, 1972-1973 (Box 25, Folder 13)
  - New York Nostalgia, 1973 (Box 25, Folder 14)
  - Mayors of New York, 1973 (Box 25, Folder 15)
  - Old New York in Early Photographs, 1853-1901, 1973 (Box 25, Folder 16)
  - Hudson River School, 1973 (Box 25, Folder 17)
  - John Pintard and His Society, 1974 (Box 25, Folder 18)
  - Deck the Halls, 1974 (Box 25, Folder 19)
  - Glass Paperweights of the N-YHS, 1974-1975 (Box 25, Folder 20)
  - Ain't I a Woman?: Woman's Rights, 1820-1920, 1975 (Box 25, Folder 21)
  - The Birth of the Continental Army, 1975 (Box 25, Folder 22)
  - Manhattan Now (2 folders), 1974-1975 (Box 25, Folder 23-24)
    Clippings pertaining to a photographic exhibition of more than 100 photos by artists such as Andre Kertesz and Andreas Feiningor.
  - Colonial Era Newspapers, 1975 (Box 25, Folder 25)
  - The Sword of Rebellion is Drawn: New York in the American Revolution, 1975 (Box 25, Folder 26)
  - The Shakers in New York State, 1975 (Box 25, Folder 27)
  - America a la Carte: Bills of Fare of the 19th and 20th Centuries, 1975 (Box 25, Folder 28)
  - Newspapers of 1775, 1975 (Box 25, Folder 29)
  - Summer in the Catskills, 1975 (Box 25, Folder 30)
  - Aaron Burr Papers, 1975-1978 (Box 25, Folder 31)
    Clippings about N-YHS's project aimed at compiling a complete edition of the papers of Aaron Burr.
  - Concert Series, 1968-1975 (Box 25, Folder 32)
  - Portrait of Mrs. Charles Jeffrey Smith (1736-1816), 1975 (Box 26, Folder 1)
    Clippings and other materials on the acquisition of the Smith portrait by Ralph Earl (1751-1801).
  - John Trumbull, 1975 (Box 26, Folder 2)
    An exhibition of John Trumbull's (1756-1843) drawings from the Fordham University collection.
  - American Genre Painting/American Folk Art, 1975 (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - Paper Currency, 1975 (Box 26, Folder 4)
    Clippings promoting an exhibition displaying paper currency used as legal tender and scrip prior to the issue of United States notes in 1863.
  - St. Nicholas Festival, 1975 (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - General Clippings, 1976 (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - N-YHS Acquisitions, 1975 (Box 26, Folder 7)
  - The New York Cabinet Maker and His Use of Space, 1976 (Box 26, Folder 8)
  - Words and Music: Sheet Music of Not So Long Ago, 1976 (Box 26, Folder 9)
  - Wine Labels, 1976 (Box 26, Folder 10)
  - History at Home: Decorative Arts, 1976 (Box 26, Folder 11)
  - Campaigns, Conventions, and Candidates: New Yorkers and the Four-Year Itch, 1976 (Box 26, Folder 12)
  - Fashions and Facades, 1976 (Box 26, Folder 13)
    Clippings promoting this exhibition of a series of 100 photographs that married fashions of a particular period with buildings constructed during the same era. Folder includes copies of the display labels for the exhibition.
  - Selling New York: Advertising from the Bella C. Landauer Collection, 1976 (Box 26, Folder 14)
  - 200 Years of American Illustration, 1976 (Box 26, Folder 15)
  - The Dutch Republic in the Days of John Adams, 1976 (Box 26, Folder 16)
  - General Clippings, 1977 (Box 26, Folder 17)
  - Women: A Kaleidoscope from the Sophia Smith Collection, 1977 (Box 26, Folder 18)
  - Remember the Ladies: Women in America, 1750-1815, 1977 (Box 26, Folder 19)
  - Jenny Lind in New York, 1977 (Box 26, Folder 20)
  - New York Then and Now: Photographs of New York in the Past, 1977 (Box 26, Folder 21)
  - Moving in the City: 300 Years of Transportation in New York, 1977 (Box 26, Folder 22)
  - Think Small: Dolls and Other Small Things, 1977 (Box 26, Folder 23)
  - General Clippings, 1978 (Box 26, Folder 24)
    This folder includes a working schedule for exhibitions between 1977 and 1979.
  - Wish You Were Here: 19th Century Resorts in New York, 1978 (Box 26, Folder 25)
  - Give Me That Old Time Religion, 1978 (Box 26, Folder 26)
  - Street Kids, 1864-1977, 1978 (Box 26, Folder 27)
  - Art of the Conservator, 1978 (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - Over Here: The Jarvis Cromwell Collection of World War I Posters, 1978-1979 (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - New York in the Forties, 1978 (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - General Clippings, 1979 (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - N-YHS Admission Policy, 1979 (Box 27, Folder 5)
  - Collecting for the Future: 25 Years of Acquisitions, 1954-1979 (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - Sheep's Heads, Eels Tartare and Little Birds on Toast, 1979 (Box 27, Folder 7)
  - Yesterday's View of the Future: Revisiting the World's Fair of '39., 1979 (Box 27, Folder 8)
  - Artists and Architects of the New York Subway, 1979 (Box 27, Folder 9)
  - A Remnant in the Wilderness: New York Dutch Scripture Paintings, 1980 (Box 27, Folder 10)
  - Knickerbocker Birthday: An Irreverent View of The New-York Historical Society, 1979 (Box 27, Folder 11)
  - Murder! Murder Most Foul!, 1979 (Box 27, Folder 12)
  - Tiffany Silver, 1980 (Box 27, Folder 13)
    Includes a checklist of pieces in the exhibition and a photographic contact sheet, presumably with images taken at the exhibition opening.
  - 55 Wall Street: A Working Landmark, 1980 (Box 27, Folder 14)
    Concerns the exhibition N-YHS installed for the re-opening of Citibank's 55 Wall Street branch, a "working landmark." Folder includes a related booklet.
  - That Belmont Look, 1980 (Box 27, Folder 15)
    Includes the press kit with photographs for the exhibition.
  - General Clippings, 1980 (Box 27, Folder 16)
  - A Panorama of Presidential Elections, 1980 (Box 27, Folder 17)
  - The Phrenology of the Land: How to Read the New York Landscape, 1980 (Box 27, Folder 18)
    Also includes clippings related to N-YHS's showing of the documentary Henry Hudson's River: A Biography.
  - New York: Art on the Road, 1980 (Box 27, Folder 19)
  - Drypoints of Mortimer Borne, 1980 (Box 27, Folder 20)
  - Small Folk: A Celebration of Childhood in America, 1980 (Box 27, Folder 21)
  - A Child's World: Toys Used by Young New Yorkers, 1700-1920, 1980 (Box 27, Folder 22)
  - The White Mountains: Places and Perceptions, 1980 (Box 27, Folder 23)
  - General Clippings, 1981 (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - Skyways: New York Aerial Views, 1981 (Box 28, Folder 2)
  - Collaboration: Artists and Architects, 1981 (Box 28, Folder 3)
  - Of the Land's Bounty: The Gardens, Meadows, and Forests of New York Province and State, 1981 (Box 28, Folder 4)
  - Manhattan Observed: Fourteen Photographers Look at New York City, 1981 (Box 28, Folder 5)
  - Shakespeare in New York, 1981 (Box 28, Folder 6)
  - The Cutting Edge: Silhouettes by Auguste Edouart, 1981 (Box 28, Folder 7)
  - Anacreon Revisited: Music from the Collection of the New-York Historical Society, 1981 (Box 28, Folder 8)
  - 200 Years of Free Masonry in New York, 1981 (Box 28, Folder 9)
    This folder includes several publications from various Free Masonry groups.
  - Twenty Years of Award Winners: The Best in Contemporary Illustration from the Society of Illustrators Annual Shows, 1981 (Box 28, Folder 10)
  - Press Reports, 1981-1982 (Box 28, Folder 11)
    This folder contains lists of coverage of 1981-1982 exhibitions mentioned in the press.
  - General Clippings, 1982 (Box 28, Folder 12)
  - George Washington Birthday Anniversary, 1982 (Box 28, Folder 13)
  - Grand Central Terminal: City Within the City, 1982 (Box 28, Folder 14)
  - MTA Photographs from the Fifth Avenue Coach Company, 1982 (Box 28, Folder 15)
  - Sailing Ships in Dutch Prints, 1982 (Box 28, Folder 16)
  - Cast with Style: 19th Century Cast-Iron Stoves, 1982 (Box 28, Folder 17)
  - FDR: A Centenial Celebration, 1982 (Box 28, Folder 18)
  - The Female Touch: The Ladies' Periodical as a Reflection of an Age, 1982 (Box 28, Folder 19)
  - A Collector's Sampler: Library Accessions, 1980-1982 (Box 29, Folder 1)
  - The Birth of New York: Nieuw Amsterdam, 1624-1664, 1982 (Box 29, Folder 2)
  - Oom Pah Pah: The Great American Band, 1982 (Box 29, Folder 3)
    This folder contains materials, including the related booklet, on the exhibition of more than 150 pieces of band-related memorabilia. Folder includes a color slide of a lithograph by Theodore Benecke from 1855 entitled, Sleighing on Broadway.
  - Koke's American Landscape Catalogue, 1982 (Box 29, Folder 4)
    Includes marketing materials for the publication of an illustrated reference book of N-YHS's collection of landscape paintings by American artists, compiled by Curator Richard J. Koke.
  - The Mayor's House: Gracie Mansion, 1982 (Box 29, Folder 5)
  - A Sampler of American Advertising from the Bella Landauer Collection, 1982-1983 (Box 29, Folder 6)
  - A Heritage to Remember: The Black Experience in New York, 1983 (Box 29, Folder 7)
  - Greetings of the Year, 1982 (Box 29, Folder 8)
  - The Sage of Sunnyside: A Washington Irving Bicentennial Celebration, 1783-1983 (Box 29, Folder 9)
    Include articles relating to this exhibition, which emphasized the relationship between Irving and N-YHS.
  - General Clippings (4 folders), 1983 (Box 29, Folder 10-13)
  - Lecture Series Schedule, 1983-1984 (Box 29, Folder 14)
  - A Celebration: American Landscape Painting, Genre Art and Drawing, 1983 (Box 29, Folder 15)
    This folder includes a photograph of the painting, Bargaining for a Horse (1835) by William Sidney Mount, that appeared in the exhibition. Includes a hand-drawn layout of the exhibition gallery indicating the placement of the various paintings and which were Richard Koke's selections.
  - N-YHS Building and Development, 1983 (Box 29, Folder 16)
  - The Esmark Collection of Currier and Ives (2 folders), 1983 (Box 30, Folder 1-2)
  - A Bridge Opens to Brooklyn, 1983 (Box 30, Folder 3)
  - Artists' Views of Central Park, 1814-1914, 1983-1984 (Box 30, Folder 4)
  - Leake and Watts Donation, 1983 (Box 30, Folder 5)
    Relates to the donation of the records of the Leake and Watts Childrens' Home in Yonkers.
  - The Library of John Pintard: Book Collecting in the New Republic, 1983 (Box 30, Folder 6)
  - Lights, Camera, Action: New York's Silent Film Studios, 1983-1984 (Box 30, Folder 7)
  - A Celebration of Opera, 1983 (Box 30, Folder 8)
  - Meyerowitz and Bernstein, 1983 (Box 30, Folder 9)
    This folder consists of materials concerning the exhibition of 36 etchings and seven paintings by William Meyerowitz and sixteen paintings by Theresa Bernstein. These works showed the Upper West Side from the early to later 20th century.
  - Shanties to Skyscrapers: Robert L. Bracklow's Photographs of Early New York, 1983-1984 (Box 30, Folder 10)
    Includes a list of the prints selected for this exhibition.
  - General Clippings, 1984 (Box 30, Folder 11)
  - N-YHS Building and Development, 1984 (Box 30, Folder 12)
  - The Cultural Pleasures of Eighteenth and Nineteenth Century New York: A Centennial Tribute to the Grolier Club, 1984 (Box 30, Folder 13)
  - Firefighting on Parade, 1700 to 1865, 1983-1984 (Box 30, Folder 14)